uh the Let's uh move to the the today's
session today I will uh continue to
explain about the uh CTC the training
part and then we also that explain about
engram language models and again today's
part will not be included in the midterm
exam
okay so at the first uh I will continue
the CTC training and the uh we actually
didn't explain about the forward and
backward algorithm in CDC so I will
explain that part and then completing
the CTC
training by the way CTC training part
will be our the coding assignment three
so we will actually carefully providing
the sufficient information so that you
guys can also passing this coding
assignment and then the uh the language
model is also by the way another
the part of the coding assignment so I
will explain about it but it's mostly
anram and I will explain about the basic
the smoothing techniques and then today
is Wednesday so we will uh have a the
weekly assignment so which sounds like a
little bit too much for you guys but
this weekly assignment is actually the
providing the hint for the uh the
current coding assignment too so uh uh
the this is designed like this and also
the slightly extending the dead line so
that you guys can uh avoid to have a big
pressure about it okay so uh let's move
to the the CTC training part this is the
review of the we have the
uh studied last time uh so first L
function is the quite simple we just
using the negative log
likelyhood conditional log
likelihood and the as a Convention of
the neural network training we just
taking the uh the minus sign but other
than that it's very similar to the uh
the EM algorithm maximum likelihood
based approaches so
the uh maximizing the likelihood would
be minimizing the negative likelihood
right so the problem is the
same just the convention is different so
I just follow the the convention of the
neuron Network and then uh how to solve
this one uh now uh that uh for CTC uh is
too complex to solve with uh the EM
algorithm so instead we use gradient Des
Center and for to that the conductor
gradient desender uh we actually have to
take the derivative and that was a kind
of main part of the the last lecture
first to take a derivative in the
parameter which corresponding to getting
the intermediate representation of the
soft Marx activation which again I will
explain more the details later that here
so just kind of if you are not very
familiar with the soft Mark Activation
so please understand that this part is
more like quite basic new network multic
classification
method so especially this second factor
is a very kind of a typical neural
network the the mar class classification
part so it is not very typical uh it is
not very kind of special for the speech
recognition actually any of the March
class
classification uh the uh problem is
actually the represented by this kind of
a form but the important part is this
the first factor which we spend a lot of
time actually it turns out that this uh
the the neuron network uh the update is
weighted by the posterior of the the
occupation probability for each the
token so this uh the posterior is
actually obtained by uh the the the
playing with the uh the the to structure
that was kind of the last year last week
no that
Monday so again I still kind of want to
recap the uh the uh the toward the
getting this uh the posterior
distribution the important part is
similar to the EM algorithm we also
focus on the the uh the gamma function
forward backward function and this is
also that called occupation probability
for uh the the uh
the for for the position of
here okay just want do not confuse that
the the token is one of the uh the
representation in the position so in
this cases for example e happen twice
right so uh this is a little bit
confusing part but please kind of the
make sure to understand the difference
and so on uh which we spend the couple
of the slide in the last time right but
anyway the for now we uh try to focus on
the uh occupation probability of uh this
point or any point of this part but
let's focus on one of the point in the
to and then try to kind of get the
probability uh of this kind of the
point and then the we kind of
the prepared the definition uh this the
probability is first represented by the
uh uh some
pass uh in the toies however we consider
all possible uh the
the the uh the passes subsequence uh
that goes to this uh the point like for
example uh the all kind of the passes
starting from here to reaching to this
uh the point uh which we should consider
okay and
similarly uh the uh
the from the point here to end of the
point uh we it can be represented by
several the uh the passes and we also
consider all all these kind of our
passes and then summation taking the
summation of all possible passes
reaching to here and then from here to
reaching to the end that would becomes a
kind of this occupation probability I
just kind of want to up it's kind of the
intuitive right it's not the easy
concept but intuitive
right uh then uh let's uh then cook this
uh the equation
uh that is the first point of the
CTC the occupation probabilities the
formulation and the I actually had a lot
of other equations here but actually all
of this kind of process is uh quite now
the familiar with you guys for example
yeah first tring is a definition just a
definition uh from here to here product
through right now I believe many people
started to you know understand this kind
of
comination and from here to here we
actually taking the conditional
Independence
assumption uh actually this conditional
Independence assumption is
uh not sure it is really B and so on so
I kind of prepared the
um the the uh want to kind of explain it
with
the um the this to here so basically uh
this means that the we ignore the uh the
dependency from T minus one to t + one
we still have a by the way dependency
from T to t + one right let's say for
example uh t t is
here t + one is here
and then T minus one is
here and as you see from the the the CTC
to there is a no kind of a rout to go
from here to the T minus one to t + one
directly right if we have a this kind of
pass the we actually have to consider
the the this dependency right T minus to
t + one is then
the had some kind of dependency but
fortunately the CTC toist actually
doesn't have the exist this kind of a
skip so that we can safely assuming uh
this conditional Independence assumption
that make
sense
okay so now that we have this kind of
our conditional Independence assumption
and finally we use a distributed
property to other uh uh uh derive uh the
factorization of the two two uh the uh
the
factor and the again I just want to
emphasize that you know the even you
know the the the speech recogition goes
to the neural network uh still and the
end to end neural network and so on
still this kind kind of the product
through conditional Independence
assumption and other kind of a tools to
mathematical tools to make the problem
tractable is very important so please uh
the remember this technique when you try
to come up with a new formulation and so
on okay and then the first part is
actually uh there are some difference
but it's quite similar to the for
variable
that we have uh that defined in the hmm
cases but in the hmm cases actually
observation is the in the kind of
argument of the probability there's some
kind of small difference and so but it's
actually doesn't have so much big
difference same for the backward
observation usually in the argument part
but the this is not very difficult to
kind of change the uh the structure by
using the base and so
so anyway the uh this are the uh uh
function term the summation of the
subsequence and then having the one
point here and this other condition and
also summation of the subsequence from
T1 uh t + one to T is actually quite
similar to the backward variable we
defined in the hmm cases
okay now it turns to to solve this
for uh uh and the backward variable by
using the the comput decursive
computation that we introduced
before so by doing that I will again the
the explain a little bit about the for
variable the for variable the most
important part is the summation over the
subsequence uh the from the uh the
beginning to
the uh the the point that we are the the
factorizing uh with the uh the
occupation
probability and we have to deal with
this the summation over the sequence but
similarly to similar to the the hmm case
is we can actually Solve IT
recursively and how to solve recursively
the first we will Define the initial
point right tal one at the initial point
and then we kind of the recursively
updating the uh the the variables and so
on and then actually first short qu
yes the question is when tal
one where we
start that is a kind of a
question this is a little bit unique in
CDC compared with the hmm so I just to
make it a
question is the question
cleer okay one more minute then
you
yeah many almost all people actually got
the the correct answer but this is just
the the difference from the hmm so I
just want to emphasize it you know the
CTC and it can be starting from either
grank or initial character so the answer
is that the it's the the initial part is
actually starting from two point and
then uh we actually uh the the starting
the initial uh the the this the alpha
probability uh we this kind of two other
variables
okay uh by the way the always the this
part is the blank so it can be actually
blank symbol and corresponding the time
frame and this why is as I mentioned
it's soft Mark function that neur
Network produce to providing it the
CDC and then second part is other can be
a kind of the first
character this also has some kind of
variables it's in this kind of example
case it can be a kind of token of s okay
and all others U three uh the u4 uh u5
U6 U7 since it cannot be studing so it's
actually the this part is
zero okay so now we kind of a set kind
of initial part and then let's go
through the kind of recursive
way and then the the now we have a a one
and a two so let's try to kind of a
compute this
one and uh how to compute it actually
the the to compute this point of the
forward
variable uh please look at the arrow
only this uh arrow that only this the
arrow exist so this means that the this
the the forward variable can be simply
computed by uh the the product uh of
this value and the uh the the uh soft
Marx uh the value
here
um and we go through this kind of a
process for one by one for all kind of a
not
and the second case
is this
point are the two arrows are coming
right so we actually then consider uh to
add the contribution of uh this forward
probability and this forward probability
and then also other multiplied by the
soft Marx values here
and we can actually continue this kind
of process Alpha 2 us3 actually only has
one Arrow so this is actually also
simply written by this one times the the
the probability Here Local probability
here and the last one as
well so this is a summary of the Second
Step uh we just you know since it is you
know very simple graph structure and
similar to hmm so similar to hmm we can
actually compute the Second Step by
using the previous the result and then
the multiplied by the the soft Marx
value and so on and we just continue
this process until small T so this is
very similar to what we have done in the
forward the
computation uh by the way uh this one uh
as I mention mention to get this kind of
the values this one we just you know
getting the one Arrow one AR right and
here we actually have to consider the
two
arcs so that we have actually the the
summation of the uh the the two arcs uh
in the kind of uh uh to get this other
next for variable but this one
fortunately only one and this one also
fortunately only one for the
contribution to compute this one this
one this one this one is one AR two ARS
one AR and one
Arc and then the other question uh the
is uh short yeah can you open it whether
do we always consider other one or two
Orcs this is a think yes
no not in this cases you know even we
move to this one or this one this one
the the number of ARS to contribute to
compute the this order is uh always one
or two that is a question
so the answer is actually
no uh there is a one case that can have
actually more than two arcs can someone
find where we can have a three
ARS yes this part and also this part as
well right yeah but this is actually
maximum three is maximum this is the
kind of a structure that you know uh the
the CTC can accept the uh this means
that this is uh the the keeping the same
state right and this one is you know the
coming from the
prank and this one is uh coming from the
previous token but of course uh in this
kind of a token uh since uh this is the
conductive uh token uh Brank must be
kind of a inserted and we cannot have a
kind of a jump here so most cases is
actually two or one but some cases it
becomes three so this is actually the
the unique the structure of
CTC so this is actually the uh the
recursive uh the equation of the CTC so
to get the kind of a alpha to compute
Alpha in the next time St
which only requires to consider the uh
same
state uh or a previous to State token I
I minus one or sometimes we also
consider I minus two but again depending
on the kind of the position uh depending
on the kind of relationship with token
uh this can be becomes one only one
contribution or two contribution but
anyway this the uh the the forward
computation is also written as a matrix
operation but Matrix is very very Spar
that's similar to
hmm so this is the the algorithm and
then we'll move to the backward
algorithm but the backward algorithm is
the similar to the uh uh last discussion
it's also quite almost same so I didn't
kind of really uh EXP about it but
backward the interesting part is that
now the there kind of condition here and
given we know this that we are
here the given we know we are here and
this uh the the the uh the summation
over the sequence uh the is the the how
it looks like this is the kind of the
backward computation and so on
and then uh similar to the uh previous
uh the forward cases let's start from
the end point tal
T then I think the question uh short
quiz question is also same I believe uh
since uh this is also the the starting
from the uh the end of the point and
then de cursively uh the uh the
uh the the backward computations happens
so we need to actually set the
initialization in the uh the end of the
the frame and then the question is uh
yes M choices anyway the
P the
end end point we should use to start
this uh the uh
calculation uh I think it's very similar
to the short quiz one so people
are understanding the question so the
answer is that again similar to the uh
the initial
part uh that we have actually
two uh the end
point in
CTC so it's you know you guys may feel
it's very obvious but this is actually
important archit in CTC so I just want
to emphasize uh it can be blank or it
can be the the last token so either of
them can be actually the end of the uh
uh end of the point of this graph so
that's why I kind of make sure to make a
quiz uh for this part and then uh in the
better the back calculation we actually
initialize this one at one
and then all the others are zero and
then taking the kind of similar
calculation that we have done before and
then I now I ski the kind of a
computation but similar to the uh the
previous cases uh to get the
uh uh to get the uh the backward
computation we have to consider the uh
in this case actually only two cases but
the if we you know
hover uh
the um if we have some point I think I
couldn't find it or this one yeah then
we actually have to consider the three x
and so on so generally the similar to
the forward uh the com
calculation uh the uh the backward
calculation also based on the three uh
terms but again this can be very SP
sometimes almost all the cases one or
two and some cases three uh and so
on so uh this is a kind of the back the
algorithm in the in CDC uh with this
kind of forward backward algorithm we
can actually uh get the computer the
occupation probability here and then
through this other occupation
probability we can move back to the
other gradient first gradient equation
and then we can actually compute the
weighted sum uh the with respect to the
Token for the gradient that
corresponding to consider the all kind
of the the toties in CTC so if we are
not very sure about CTC I recommend it
to always kind of write the to this and
then you guys can kind of understand the
the more details about the cgc other
structure and I kind of put this kind of
a lecture here in this timing rather
than kind of explaining about the ne
Network and so on because again I want
to kind of emphasize that the algorithm
is very similar to the for backward
algorithm so this is a kind of intention
putting this other
CTC estimation process here uh any
question for this CTC training part
including last
lecture I hope you guys know enjoy some
similarity and some
difference okay so cool and actually
duing I was also writing this kind
of the the preparing this materials and
writing to I actually came up with a new
two ctcs so if some of you are in
interested in maybe that we can work
together one CTC the possible CTC is
actually very similar to
hmm uh the two state every time we have
a two State left to right two State uh
this is actually also uh the uh the uh
the probably uh the maybe there's
something wrong that I have never
implemented so but probably this can
also perform the speech I believe uh
because that the the important part is
that whether we can distinguish the
repeated token or not right but this
case is you know same token is actually
you know goes from one to two and then
going back to one so this means that the
if there these are uh two tokens are uh
the uh repeated token then this number
does go back to the one means that the
we always have a boundary here right so
by using the two H uh two State CTC we
actually don't have to include a Brank
and we can actually provide the speech
condition based on this the uh the
architecture so but not sure that it's
working but at least theoretically this
one should also make a speech condition
and another architecture that to I came
up with is this
one uh so the I didn't fully emphasize
but the another important difference of
the hmm and CDC if you remember is that
hmm I actually explained that we usually
put the silence uh the beginning and
silence end or even sometimes actually
put in short for
between the word and so
on however CTC actually this the
function was uh the the uh conducted by
the Brank symbol but Brank symbol also
has a meaning of for example the
repeating the same token or using the
Brank token so it's Brank can also be
behaved of duration
part and the blank also is be the
important rule to make a distinction
between the concu characters
right so Brank actually has a three
rules one would be possibly silence the
other would be a duration model and the
third would be that kind of repetition
the distinction of the repetition and so
on so the which is maybe good you know
just one symbol to do this kind of three
roles but sometimes actually silence is
also very important information
but CTC actually cannot well model the
silence we cannot interpret the silence
actually after the we get the blank and
so on so then that I came up with a new
architecture which is know starting from
Silence beginning and then we already
have the short pause so if this is a
this is a example is a character but
this uh the token is like a word and so
on it's possibly the the the the short
POS can be inserted right but short P
cannot be inserted so that's why it
actually can be
skipped and then we also have uh the the
blank symbol we have to include because
otherwise we we might not uh distinguish
this one and this one and so on so this
may also be another possible uh the way
to kind of realize spech condition I
believe and I just want to mention is
that again CTC
this kind of structure is very cool very
kind of well designed but it would not
be the one kind of other the the perfect
answer probably we may explore more
about the uh the this kind of topology
uh of the the network this is actually
not so much studied recently people just
let's say using CTC uh and so on so I
actually want to repit this part
especially I'm very interested in
silence part which is not very kind of
explicitly modeled in CTC but anyway
this is just side side
note okay so uh the last comment about
the
CTC actually the uh the the uh Professor
via R course the uh the introduction to
deep running is very very good I also by
the way watched the the the his YouTube
video even I want to actually attend his
the lecture which will be in the next
week no week after next no it's after
the the fall break but unfortunately I
will be the the not
available but I if you guys taking this
course I definitely recommend you to
check this course and you guys can also
get the uh the the information from the
YouTube uh and and so on I think the
this is the most kind of uh the uh the
concise the complete uh the the
explanation about CTC I would
say and the I also kind of often defer
the original uh the paper from the uh
the
graves okay so now uh the the completely
changing the topic and then try to kind
of finish the language modeling part
uh so because we first starting from the
each component right uh uh feature
extraction acoustic modeling lexon
language model and then we exp the the
uh the discussed about feat extraction
and we spend a lot of time for the
acoustic modeling and then we also kind
of the little bit the move to the CTC
which is end to end but we actually
didn't explained about the language
modeling part by the way Leon part as I
mentioned in the the beginning is
basically just using the dictionary so
in this lecture I kind of skip the
detailed explanation so but anyway the
now that the final component that I
didn't fully explain is language
modeling and then I want to explain it
first with the classical Manner and then
later we use the neural the based
approaches and so one but probably some
of you might kind of forget this kind of
structure so I just have a Sr slide to
review the old component fast speech
recognition you know and this is also
good to review for the uh toward the uh
the uh midterm exam just a so first know
speech condition always starting from PW
given all and the CTC is directly
the tackling this one but the hmm based
approach is basically kind of compos the
three the part and then we spend a lot
of time to just explain about this the
acostic modeling
part and then we using the hmm GMM and
then the finally kind of the providing
the B algorithm or B algorithm and so on
that was the kind of the
uh the our lecture uh in the last week
and then this week we kind of discuss
about the CTC and so on but basically uh
the the uh we are working on this kind
of a costing modeling
part and then the the uh next comp part
is the we simply uh the uh using the
existing uh the the pronunciation
dictionary and then uh we also often use
the CMU pronunciation uh dictionary to
uh deal with this kind of problem and so
one but today uh uh I will also bit
focus on this one
because possibly it could be a uh
midterm exam
but
okay then the uh I will explain about
the language modeling
part for this language modeling part I
actually refer to this paper um
empirical study of smoothing technique
for language modeling this is also very
famous uh review paper for language
model and I basically follow this paper
and so on and as you can see this is
also from CMU so many of techniques are
from CMU and many of the good papers
also from
CMU okay so uh the language model
nowadays it's super kind of the exciting
approaches happens right but
unfortunately within this lecture within
this kind of a today's course it is not
like a fancy language model it's still
kind of a classical language model but I
which is still important so I want to
explain with some word so the language
model is to kind of get the the the
prior probability of the world sequence
again the uh the yeah it's actually
prior probability uh the originally
language model is used a prior
probability for speech equ machine
translation but now language model
itself becomes a kind of a main model so
I feel that you know the the the model
the use of the model application could
be changed depending on the the time
feel like that yeah used to be language
model is actually such kind of topic but
anyway this kind of sentence itself to
be the model is not easy and then what I
usually what we usually can of solve
this problem is that we actually taking
this as a consider it as a sequence and
then uh the factorize uh this uh the uh
the uh probability uh by using the uh
rule so can you answer this part yeah
it's can be also called product protic
chain but this one is a part of the L
even larger langage model this kind of
probability uh the the processing is
very important so that please remember
it okay again the the uh how to deal
with uh this estimation is very
important and then first part of this
lecture I will use the kind of a
technique called anram and then the
second part which is the probably after
the fall break and then also go through
some neural network and then we'll kind
of repat it here again uh in this cases
we using a neural
network okay so anagram is actually uh
uh the very kind of similar concept that
we have used for the hidden marov model
we actually are the using the marov
assumption
in this condition so for example this
one uh 1 to IUS one right so this means
that this a
subsequence and then if the sentence
becomes very long and then condition
also becomes very wrong and it is very
difficult to actually estimate this
probability so anram is are the very uh
intuitive
we just
forget we just forget the
history which is okay for the uh some of
the application especially speech
recognition and uh how many word we
usually keep in the speech do you guys
know
that only three or four yeah but that is
enough uh for speech recognition because
speech recognition is more like the uh
the uh transcribe the kind of what we
are talking right of course the uh the
language model semantic information is
very helpful but uh at the same time we
want to kind of the the
straightforwardly convert what we have
saying we actually don't need so much
important contextual information and so
on semantic information so on so that's
why we actually using a 2 to three or 3
to four the the history for the the
language model and that is actually
quite enough for many of the speech
recogition
application however of course everyone
may know this assumption is not actually
correct right uh this are the two
sentences I want to go to the CMU campus
and the do want to go to the CMU campus
the second one very nonsense right but
the if we only you know consider the
history of you know until two or three
we go to this area this comput the
probability and this probability is
actually same regardless of whether we
have you know this kind of very
important distinction so on so yeah
anram is not perfect but just kind of
consider the local context it is very
powerful
and then another part of the nice the
another kind of good part of the the
anram is that we can easily solve it
with a maximum likelihood uh estimation
and I just kind of taking the the
equation here but uh it is actually the
the the first the mass is also not so
difficult but the more interesting part
is that the solution is very
intuitive actually the maximum
likelihood
solution uh of this kind of probability
is that just a ratio of the
count more world would be more likely
happen so this is a kind of Maximum
likelihood enam solution and this is
again just kind of sweeping the entire
Corpus and just kind of the getting the
C of the the word or the uh the in the
anram cases we may consider kind of a a
combination of the two word and so on so
it's a little bit complicated but still
just kind of sweeping the data
accumulating the count and then taking
the ratio uh this becomes the
probability so it is very intuitive
right so I can give you some example so
in this example I will use the unigram
which is the the most kind of the
approximated method it's actually
doesn't consider any
history uh just kind of consider the the
word itself and then uh the let's the
count let's for for example training
data is only this
one usually of course it can be the
million billion sentences but the just
consider only this one is the the
training data and then let's do the
maximum lik estimation how to do that we
just kind of the the comp comp the count
of how often each word appeared in this
sentence right and actually only two to
are appeared twice and then others are
the only appeared once so it is a kind
of intuitive right because again this to
often happens so it can have a more
higher prob probability is are kind of a
Mak sense uh in terms of the uh this
the the approximation and so on however
it is
too the too much approximation right
don't even this other unigram doesn't
consider any history and so on and then
what happens is that even switch the
order of the sequence since they don't
have uh the uh the history information
actually the probability becomes
equal so uh
the for example the want to go I to and
want to go the I want to go to I want
to
the uh want to go I to and I want to go
to become the same probability it is
very kind of weird right but this one is
actually simply solved by uh consider
the
history and then we actually started to
get some kind of order it's still not
the perfect it's still kind of you know
have some the the uh the the issues but
if we consider the longer history and so
on uh this kind of approximation is the
more kind of the the the the precise and
then the it's getting the better and the
better and then Bagram cases the still
kind of the maximum likelihood
estimation is very
simple so Bagram cases is we have to
have a kind of consider the uh the uh
two consecutive the word uh the other
kind of unit and then uh the count is
actually represented by this so uh the
if the the the two pairs of the word
consecutive two pairs of the word
happens and then we just kind of
checking the count and then the taking
the uh
the normalizing it with a probability
and it becomes the Byram probability a
triam the forr basically same and so on
and then that we may think that oh then
if we make it for example thousand gram
and so on we can you know
even consider the entire sentence right
but it's actually not so easy to make
this kind of the part to be extended so
one of the big issue is a zero count
problem so this is a one example but
anyway the again if the training data is
only this
one and then uh the count combination of
the count is very SP right almost all
part is zero
actually almost all part is
zero and then let's take the maximum
likelihood
estimation this means that these kind of
probability is completely zero this
means that
the go I or the the the when I kind of
slightly change the kind of sentence
from I want to go to my office to I go
to my office then this Byram doesn't
exist probability becomes zero speech
condition actually doesn't output this
sentence so the the more kind of a
context is actually making a risk
of the the making the probability
estimation very bad and even zero count
is means that it doesn't appear at all
so we should avoid this kind of issues
and so
on okay then how to deal with this kind
of problem people are actually are the
uh the proposing the several techniques
and this are the are the uh techniques
of avoiding the zero probability is
called
smoothing so language model uh
especially in the engram based model
smoothing is a very important concept so
without smoothing actually it was not
working so I will explain about three
smoothing techniques uh in this lecture
oh uh
I have 20 minutes right but I also need
to explain about the weekly assignment
okay uh let me
try
um so first uh the smoothing method most
simple smoothing method is to actually
anyway add
something uh even this is the count zero
so we want want to avoid zero so we just
kind of add
something and then we at least avoiding
the
zero so this other method is called
additive smoothing or laas smoothing and
so
on and this one of course you know if
the this the is a kind of let's say
hyper
parameter if this part becomes zero it's
exactly maximum likelihood
and if this one is by the way very
large and then adding this one means
that adding this kind of a account to
all the kind of vocabulary and so on so
this means that this if this kind of
alpha becomes very large the uh the it
becomes equal
probability uh across the vocabulary uh
and so on it's not very bad and then
just tuning this part and then at least
we can avoid this probability and very
simply avoid the the that language model
and so on but this is actually quite uh
the uh we can just avoid the zero
probability but it usually doesn't the
powerfully
working
instead uh the I think this is the most
practical First the uh the smoothing
method is that let's for example uh
compute the
Bagram maximum
likelihood however we also kind of
linearly interpret the
unigram and you could imagine unigram
actually doesn't have a zero count
problem Bagram has a zero count problem
so if the the Bagram has a zero count
issue and then we just using the unigram
probability we just kind of are removing
the history it's a quite kind of reason
assumption and this Lambda is control
parameter by the way this can be also
used higher n again for example this
part is trigram and this part can be
Byram and so on more are the the the
context and then the the data becomes
the more spse and then using the the uh
the uh the the the lower n uh run and
then the smoothing it is actually quite
reasonable so this is actually the the
the the initially uh the used the the
the language model uh
technique and then uh there are several
other language model uh technique and so
on and then today I will also explain
about the N
smothing okay
by the way the uh some people may
notice um smoothing technique are
actually usually are the named by the
humans name so jck marer they actually
both working at the IBM and then propos
this approaches and the uh with and Bell
these are also two person names and the
smoothing and the ne n is also two
people's are the uh name so if you want
to be
famous
uh my suggestion is working on the
smoothing technique but in this case uh
you should only ask the one person to up
up to two
people and then your name and your Co
name can be you know the the the become
a kind of the this kind of the
techniques uh in the uh uh in the the
algorithm so it's the I don't know
smoothing also comes from the the
information Theory and so on it's uh the
such kind of culture may happen but
usually computer science we don't use
the humans name as the algorithm right
so again if you want you can try
that okay so
uh okay I will I'll do my best to uh
expain NE night
smoothing so NE night smoothing is
actually
interesting uh the it is actually
opposite we actually are taking the uh
the removing the
count uh instead of adding the account
which may actually uh the increase the
kind of risk uh over
the uh the over the zero count but we
usually actually how to say making this
kind of a condition if you know a
denominator is uh the the uh the less
than zero and then it we just using the
zero and then this other smoothing part
is just becomes a kind of probability
and so on so but this uh the approach is
first discounting the uh the probability
and this the discounting is actually
quite reasonable uh because the menu
actually training data is biased and
having actually more data than we
expected for specific some kind of
accounting issues so the my the the
discounting is is actually the making
this kind of bias data to be mitigated
so this first part is taking the
discounting uh by the way this are the
uh uh uh the Lambda part is and the
Delta part is
related and then second ter is the most
important
part uh the previously uh in the jck M
smoothing we actually using the Bagram
and then the interpolated by the
unigram but second part is actually
instead of using the unigram we use a
very other special the the the smoothing
the probability so which I will try to
explain it
so this is actually quite famous problem
called the the the uh the San Francisco
uh
problem so let's say uh for example the
uh the we
this uh word are not appeared in our
training
data and then and we need a smoothing
technique to the infa this probability
that is our problem so on but anyway do
you think which one is more the likely
occur leading glasses and leading
Francisco the obvious leading grasses
right yeah however if we do the unigram
smoothing what's
happened actually s
Francisco
is quite largely heat uh in the training
data more than the grasses
unfortunately so if using the for
example the uh the unigram other uh the
the smoothing techniques and then
Francisco would be actually selected
which is wrong
right and then the uh actually we want
to avoid this kind of smoothing and so
on
by the way uh why Francisco so often
happens San Francisco yes exactly so
actually the this the the among the
three
3,000 over the the
90% is about San
Francisco so uh due to this kind of a
issue in the count if we using the UN
unigram the San Francisco H sorry the
leading Francisco would be getting the
higher probability so we should avoid it
we should try to kind of find another
way to uh the the Mak the the make a
probability and so on and then as I
mentioned s Francisco is quite kind of a
The Limited uh the pair
mostly the the before the Francisco
would be son or some other Mis or it's
very limited while grasses may have a
lot of actually the variations in the
kind of a context and so on so this can
be more likely right so instead of
checking the
count in the ne night smoothing we
actually just checking the how many
variation before
this kind of a award and so on again
Francisco that it can be son or Mis or
very few uh and then the glasses it can
be colored holding world it's quite
actually many and I actually counted
this one in the one of the the Copus the
Francisco variation is
58 may have you know this uh the
prefix not prefix it's the the previous
uh the that token variation can be 58 by
the way I saw that it's very small but
it's actually more than I expected uh
but still you know grasses is more right
80 to 8 variations
happens so let's use this one as a
probability we just kind the ignore the
count and then just kind of using the
variation uh of the context as a
probability uh that that is another ni
smoothing so by the way I want to
emphasize that this one is only for the
smoothing part it is kind of based on
the variations but the original part if
we have a more count and so on uh we
just using the the normal engram so uh
by combining this kind of two approaches
uh we can actually the
accurately uh the providing the prob
ility uh in the uh the in the case that
if we don't have the sufficient the data
and so on of course that if we have a
tons of data we don't need so much
smoothing and so on so it's a more like
a kind of balance of the
issue and lastly uh I will also explain
about how to kind of evaluate the
language
model of course One Direction will be to
use the speech condition first estimate
the langage model and then combine it to
the speech condition and then evaluating
the word er so this is more kind of
intuitive ways more kind of the the the
application oriented evaluation but uh
this is actually having some cost speech
condition is actually more
computationally expensive than language
model so instead the people are using
the pity here this is actually quite
simple first we get the kind of model
the estimator model and so on and
through it the Computing that actually
likely
good and then if this the likelihood is
higher this means that this kind of a
model can well the the the represent the
test data right so this the perplexity
is quite often used as the measure to
evaluate the language
model and then let's check the kind of
performance of the the the smoothing
method and the anram method and so on so
additive smoothing is the one that I
mentioned just kind of adding the alpha
to the uh the numerator and the
denominator and Alpha is the kind of
tuning
parameter uh and then please check the
the 2 to three actually it's a the
reasonable Improvement in terms of the
Pard uh the
uh 10% of the power is improved but
actually uh more the the uh the the the
context it doesn't improve the
performance move to the N smoothing it
actually have a quite significant
Improvement in terms of publicity uh
compared with additive and it's actually
also having a very good improvement from
two to three but 3 to four is
marginal so even we have more context we
actually have a more kind of issue in
the zero or lower count probability
smoothing happens approximation happens
so unless we we have infinite data
actually that this the engram based
approaches cannot be well scaled to the
the large end but again this is actually
the important for speech conition
because for speech
local context is important and I'm yes
that nowadays a lot of neural language
models are used and so on but still the
anram is also used in speech recogition
and there is a kind of big the reason
one is that anyway this model is too
simple so that we don't have a kind of a
bias or hallucination so on which is
quite kind of a the difficult issue in
the large language model and so on we
don't want to change our kind of you
know the speech recognition result to be
the the deed with some large language
model and completely different sentence
right so uh this kind of part is
actually actively studied uh and the the
this can be the the the one of the
important research the problems uh now
uh but anyway uh the the the anagram uh
is uh with the smoothing technique it is
kind of still used for many of the
speech conion
system uh that is for this the lecture
part any questions